Guide to the William Sennett Photograph Collection ALBA.PHOTO.199
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
William Sennett Photographs
1937-1938
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sennett, William, 1914-
ALBA.PHOTO.199
0.25 Linear Feet (1 Document Box); 88 negatives sized from 2 ¼ x 3 ¾ inches to 3 ½ x 2 ½ inches.
As a youth, William Sennett was a member of the Young Communist League; he later became a paid functionary of the Communist Party, USA, and still later a successful corporate executive. A metalworker from Cicero, IL, Sennett served in the International Brigades in the Spanish Civil War as political commissar of a transportation regiment -- Second Squad, Second Regiment de Tren. The collection contains non-combat images of an armored car crew, artillery crew, motorcycle corps, scouts, troops heading to the front, performing support activities and relaxing, bombed/shelled buildings, Spanish nurses and other civilians, Spanish street scenes and panoramas.
Provenance
The William Sennett Photograph Collection was donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Corine Thornton in 1997. The collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
William (Bill) Sennett (né Snesetsky or Snestzki) was raised in Chicago and participated in hunger marches, organizing in the South Side black community and other political activities as a Section Organizer for the Young Communist League. He was a metalworker, living in Cicero, IL, when he volunteered for service on the Loyalist side in the Spanish Civil War. He arrived in Spain in March 1937 and served in the International Brigades as political commissar of a transportation regimen -- Second Squad, Second Regiment de Tren. His brother, Maurice (or Morris), also served in Spain. Bill Sennett served in the army air force during World War II, and returned to Chicago after the War and became a paid functionary of the Communist Party. He broke with the Party after 1956, moved his family to California and eventually became a successful businessman as president of a multimillion-dollar trucking business headquartered in San Francisco. (For additional biographical information, see William Sennett: Communist Functionary and Corporate Executive, an oral history conducted by Marshall Windmiller, Bancroft Library, University of California, Berkeley, 1984. Copy at the Tamiment Library.)
Scope and Content Note
Series I. Negatives. The William Sennett Collection contains 88 negatives including non-combat images of an armored car crew, artillery crew, motorcycle corps, scouts, troops heading to the front, performing support activities and relaxing, bombed/shelled buildings, Spanish nurses and other civilians, Spanish street scenes and panoramas.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic. The negatives are identified by four numbers separated by colons. The first number refers to the collection number, the second to the box number, the third to the folder number, and the fourth to the individual negative. For example, the first negative in this collection is numbered 199:1:1:1.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I, Negatives
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
William Sennett Papers, ALBA #199
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Negatives (photographic); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Pictorial works; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Teruel (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- International brigades.; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; Sennett, William, 1914-
- Series I: Negatives
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, Armored Car Crew, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, Artillery Crew, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, Downed Airplane, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, Motorcycle Corps, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, Scout/Surveying, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, Sentries, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, Support Activities, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, Troops Heading to the Front, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Behind the Lines: Daily Life of the Soldiers, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Behind the Lines: Rest and Relaxation, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bombed/Shelled Buildings, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Fortifications, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Groups: Unidentified, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Individuals: Unidentified, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Military Vehicles: Trucks, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Monument: Spain, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Spanish Cities: Street Scenes, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Spanish Civilians, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Spanish Civilians: Workers, Laundrywomen, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Spanish Communist Party: Headquarters, Teruel, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Spanish Landscapes: Panoramas, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Spanish Nurses, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Spanish Villages: Street Scenes, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 24)